- Good afternoon everyone.
Once again, Don Daves-Rougeaux,
Senior Advisor to Chancellor Christian's Office,
Workforce Economic Development, Strategic Partnerships,
and part of the generative AI team led by Craig Hayward.
Really super excited about our concluding panel for today.
And I want to,
before we jump into that panel, I wanna take a little bit
of time to orient ourselves to some of the work
and connections to last year's summit,
and then introduce one of our key partners.
So last year, well, let me start here.
I would say this, so part of what we want you to do here is
to build relationships, to network, to meet people.
We want our college faculty
and classified professionals
and administrators to connect with our industry partners,
with our partners in labor and state agencies,
but also with partners
who are here from other higher ed institutions,
or even our K-12 partners who may be here.
Last year, we had an opportunity to pilot
or demo a very specific tool.
And that opportunity came as result
of just a single conversation
that we were having in a hallway.
It was very opportune as well,
because we happened
to be having our faculty professional development committee
that was going to be meeting on Friday,
and that actually will be happening again this year.
On Friday, that group will continue to convene
and think about how we do professional development
for our faculty across the system.
And so we were able to start up
that conversation in passing.
And I am known as well,
I always say this,
but I'm trying to change my vernacular on this
because of climate, but you know,
I'm a boil the ocean kind of person.
I like to run really fast with cautionary guardrails,
but I like to go.
So I tried to change it to green, the desert,
but then I thought, there's nothing wrong
with desert environments as well,
so I gotta get away from that.
So we're just gonna change things really fast, okay?
A lot of things at the same time, really fast in our system.
So I approached now Vice Chancellor
for Academic Affairs, James Todd, and I said, "Hey James,"
and another faculty member's on that committee,
Michelle, and I said, "Hey James,
can I just take one hour of your six hour meeting time?
Just one hour, one hour is all we need."
He said, "Don." If you know James, he's like, "Don."
And I said, "Okay, how about 45 minutes?"
He said, "Okay, let me go check with the committee."
And the committee said, "Yes."
And as it were, we already had two of our faculty members
on that professional development committee
who were innovators in our system
that were already using the tool.
So I got those two faculty members
with our guests member I'm gonna bring up now,
and they said, we will use that 45 minutes
and we will demo this project.
And as a result of that,
we were able to launch the Playlab pilot
and Playlab took off with the level of enthusiasm
that we could never have imagined in that moment.
We sent out an interest form
and in 10 days we had 879 people sign up
saying that they were interested in doing a Playlab,
a professional learning community.
454 of those 800 plus folks who signed up,
and these are classified professionals, faculty, et cetera,
actually went through that professional learning community.
And this is the power of moving at the pace of innovation,
having a bias for action.
My mom would always say, "Maybe,"
and I never knew if maybe meant yes or no.
More often than not, it meant no,
but occasionally gave me time to negotiate to get to yes.
But if we act with the bias of action,
even if we are uncertain around what the results might be,
we might find that innovation is at our fingertips.
And that there are folks in our system who are hungry
for these kinds of experiments and opportunities.
And we act with the reality that we might fail, right?
And we can't be afraid to fail.
I was a hurdler in high school and college.
The first time I went over a hurdle,
I literally fell on my face.
That's 'cause I raised the hurdle way too high,
'cause I didn't know that you could put them down lower.
I learned that, maybe start with a low bar.
But all that to be said, it was a great moment in time.
And we have done some great work
with Playlab since that time.
And I'm pleased to be able to bring
to you today, to the stage, my partner in crime
who is a faculty member at UC Berkeley
in the Graduate School of Education
and leads UC Berkeley's Changemaker program.
And you may have heard us talk about our AI Fellows
and then we also have this other group
called our AI Changemakers
who are folks who applied to be fellows.
But despite their incredible talent,
we just didn't have enough space.
So we reached out to them and said, we would like for you to
stay involved in this, figure out a way to engage you.
And I know there are some of the Changemakers
that are here in the audience today.
And I was very intentional about using
that term Changemakers
because I wanted to think down the road.
I'm a gamer.
So gamers we're all about down board thinking
and knowing that at some point down the road we would want
to build a formal partnership with UC Berkeley,
and their Changemaker program.
And so those conversations are in play
and if when we get there,
we will have already built a cohort and a cadre of faculty
of classified professionals,
and administrators in our system, across our entire system
to lean into that partnership with depth.
So at this time, I'd like to go ahead
and bring up to stage, Dr. Christyna Serrano,
also known as Dr. C.
And she will talk a little bit about
what that partnership looks like
from the side of UC Berkeley.
Dr. C.
(audience applauding)
- Hi.
Hi everybody. Okay, so first I want
to start this conversation off with saying I'm the product
of a community college.
(audience cheering) (audience applauding)
Thank you.
I was first in my family
to go to college and I went to Hartnell College
and then transferred to UC Berkeley.
Woo-hoo. Go Panthers and Go Bears.
And I apologize, my slides are text heavy
and this is a no no, we know this, right?
This is a no no, so I apologize,
but you know, we got lots of things going on.
So try and ignore my slides
and hopefully you'll hear the story,
which is, I can't walk, I wanna walk,
but then like there's no mic.
So this is a true privilege and an honor.
So a year ago I was at the first Future Summit
and I was a participant.
And as Don was describing,
he and I had chatted about, okay,
how can we do this work together?
And I got a chance to shout out to Havi and Scotty,
if you're here.
Woo-hoo.
We basically, Havi
and I were both in the Relay Graduate School
of Education's Playlab Professional Learning Community.
And from there I saw how powerful of a tool it was.
And so one of my classes
that I teach at Berkeley in the School of Ed,
it's called Critical Studies and Education,
partners students with social impact ed tech organizations,
so they can do a Changemaker project.
And the goal of these projects is to really show students
that you can have an impact in the field of education
beyond traditional classroom teaching, which is great,
but it invites people to consider
how they are always educators
and learners all at the same time.
But also the grind that it takes to be in the field
and to learn skills around what we call the three C's
in the work of Changemaker, critical thinking,
communication, and collaboration.
So Playlab was one of those partners that year.
'cause I felt like it was such a powerful tool
and I'd asked Yusef,
who's our co-founder, what are you trying to do?
What goal can I help you advance
that would also give my students an opportunity
to do this work, to do this really important work
that we're doing at Playlab now?
And they were not initially a higher education sort
of focused platform.
It was K-12 and they were growing organically from there.
And so then I said, "Hey John,
I have a project for you.
What do you think?"
And so hence began this year long journey.
It's crazy because I used to work at Stanford
as Director of Early Career Online Business Education,
but I recently left Stanford in order to join Playlab
as head of community learning and growth
as part of this journey.
So I'm really excited to be here with you today
and talk about what we're doing.
And hopefully, I'll just get the opportunity.
I hope you'll say hi to me.
I hope you'll reach out to me.
I'm so interested in collaborating with you.
But about Playlab, for those of you that might not born,
it was born in 2022, it was actually,
there was a product that was for the team,
the founding team, they made something on GPT 3
that was founded by Google and that achieved acquisition.
But the team started to notice
that despite the success in these commercial AI
and research applications
that they were doing at MIT,
educators weren't really using them.
So that's when Playlab was founded
because it was this notion
that educators shouldn't be passed down ed tech tools
and not have a say in sort of determining like
what do these tools do for us,
but be creators
of these tools rather than just passive recipients.
So what happened was when they sort
of gave educators the tools in terms of being able
to build their own chatbots
or own AI tools in order
to solve problems in specific contexts,
that these were really powerful things
that educators were building to solve these problems.
And they were really cracking like the nut, you could say,
of how do we solve like some wicked problems
in the classroom,
not all the way, but really starting to make some headway
and how can you use this application
in these particular ways.
So it really created some fundamental shifts around
how teaching and learning has started to happen.
And we're seeing that a lot with Playlab.
So the thing that also is really important
to know about Playlab is it's a non-profit organization.
And one of the reasons
that Playlab is a non-profit organization is
because we're really mindful, very thoughtful about
how do we protect our young people
and protect really what's the responsibility, right,
of like this technology is very disruptive
and how do we support our educators in being able
to manage it, to think about how to integrate it.
And so one of the things was like, hey,
our systems are already,
like pedagogy as an educator,
it's already kind of broken, right?
The systems are already hard.
Education is, there's already systems in place
that aren't always serving students
and AI can, unfortunately, just kind of reinforce that
and exacerbate it further.
So premature scaling is really not something
we wanted to do.
If you do so,
it can just really over fit into an already broken system
and kind of further exacerbate that and create real harm.
So in this case, we wanted to create something
that enabled people to play, to feel curious and feel safe
because Playlab is a school safe platform.
So even though you can run your tools on all the models,
all the foundational models like ChatGPT 3
or ChatGPT, sorry, Anthropic's Claude,
none of that data gets seen when you're in the play space.
And we wanted people to feel comfortable to experiment
and to co-create with their students.
So it's your ability to, even if you're using Google Gemini
or you're using ChatGPT,
even if you create a bot in those contexts,
you can never look under the hood,
you can't see the conversations,
you can't collectively build with people.
It is a very specifically built for educators
and by educators tool.
So we just saw the creative power
that this global community of educators have built,
the kinds of tools that have come out of it.
And so being a nonprofit enables us to think about
what is the public infrastructure that we can create,
where we can democratize access to these tools
and where we can cultivate voices for our students
and our educators who can have a say
in what this future should be
and have the skills to be able to navigate
that future workforce where it's really a much more
about machine/human collaboration.
As head counts start to go down,
there's more management that has to happen
in the future of work
where your team members are essentially agentic AI tools.
All right, so with that we have an official announcement.
So what was initially a pilot
and it was crazy, we were all working for free, ask Miya.
And it was all volunteer
and all of you that were in that cohort, I appreciate you,
and that was all voluntary.
So as Dawn said, it was about 800 folks interested,
but we ended up with 400 plus faculty
and staff in a four week series
of a professional learning community.
And it's amazing how much has come from that.
And I think many of the AI fellows
are pretty much Playlabbers.
Many of you may be using it in your classroom already.
And so it's really representative of a partnership
that is meant to be built on trust, collaboration,
and shared values rather
than a top down kind of technology implementation.
So our approach is really about how do we build tools.
So you guys use it, you start asking me.
I was just having conversation with Bobby that like, hey,
can we have this attribution, right,
where, you know, it's a new form of scholarship.
These bots are running on systems prompts
which reflect the metacognition that we're having
to develop in our students, for example.
And as you author these chatbots
that are solving real problems in your context
and other folks remix it
because we're set up as a community of practice,
how do we keep that line going?
But additionally, so many, you know, chatbots are remixed
and used for silo bot for just all kinds of functionality
and it's really helping others across the classroom.
And so as people are building things, I just love
how much they say, "You know,
it'd be really cool if it could do this."
And so our small engineering team at Playlab
works really hard to basically be responsive to the feedback
that you're giving us of like,
"I really wish it could do this in my classroom.
If it could do this, it would be a game changer."
So that's how we're building essentially in collaboration
with educators like yourself
and staff like yourself in order to improve what the future
of education and work looks like.
So I have three strategies that I'm gonna tell you about,
about how we're deploying this at a much larger scale
across the system,
even though the 400 plus faculty represented the full state
of California and all the colleges within it.
I'm just gonna go straight to these slides.
So the first pillar is kind
of this comprehensive learning experience.
So what we do is this one-on-one series
where you're doing a foundational sort of,
this is what generative AI is,
and this is how you build a system prompts,
and this is how you configure a chatbot
so that it can do all these powerful things
and help you advance your goals in the community.
Then we move into tool ones,
which is much more like leveling up your bots
and really taking the feedback
that you might get in your analytics
and supporting just deeper innovation.
And we're definitely including the staff in this engagement
because we're all working together,
faculty, staff, and students,
and you can have your students build as well.
So the second pillar is that we have a Solution Studio.
As I mentioned already,
all of you have been building really important tools
that are applicable across context,
and so we wanna make sure that those tools are available
for you to remix.
And then additionally, we just have, like I said,
co-developed AI systems.
We are not building for profit, right?
We can't say this about the big guys who are not necessarily
engaged in doing this work.
They have private interests
and we have public interest.
So we are really working with the system to ensure
that this platform is built for all of you
to support the most vulnerable populations to create,
as Chancellor Christian was saying earlier,
it's equity of access, democratization, et cetera.
All right, so the scale of this partnership is unique
by virtue of the fact
that the community colleges in California are so big.
So I'm getting told like it's like wrap it up.
Don, you took too much time.
You took all the time Don. Sorry.
(audience laughing)
All right, so the vision, we are supporting the vision 2030
and this AI ready workforce.
We really are trying to think about, okay,
how do we upskill?
But then additionally,
how are we creating those only human skills?
How do we cultivate and anchor people in those skills
while also advancing the tooling?
So I think that's it. Thank you.
I appreciate your time and listening to me.
I hope to see you there. Bless you.
(audience applauding)
- I'm here to take more time.
Okay, so a librarian, a college president,
and a computer science researcher
and a chatbot building education faculty member
walk onto a stage.
Now this isn't the setup
for a joke about artificial intelligence
taking over higher ed, though honestly it might as well be.
So welcome to Agentic AI in Higher Education:
Preparing the Future Workforce
Through Strategic Partnerships,
where we've assembled
what might be the most unlikely dream team
since the Avengers, but with significantly more caffeine
and considerably less superpowers.
Though our librarian would argue
that finding obscure research papers
in under 30 seconds is basically a superpower.
Our college president brings the big picture vision.
And by big picture we mean trying to figure out how
to explain to the board why we need a budget approval for AI
that might actually become smarter than all of us combined.
Our lead librarian has gone from shushing people
to teaching them how to have productive conversations
with chatbots.
Talk about career evolution.
Our computer science researcher is here to remind us
that we think AI can do,
and to remind us that what we think AI can do
and what it actually can do are two very different things.
And our education faculty member
has been busy building chatbots,
probably because grading papers
at 2:00 AM finally drove them to seek digital assistance.
Together, they'll explore the burning question,
how do we prepare students for a future
where their study buddy might be an AI agent,
their research assistant could be a sophisticated algorithm
and their biggest academic challenge might be learning
to collaborate with machines that never need coffee breaks.
Buckle up folks,
this is going to be either brilliantly insightful
or cautionary tale about what happens when educators try
to outsmart the technology they're teaching.
Either way it should be entertained.
I'll introduce you to our panel.
(bright music)
(audience applauding)
- Good afternoon everyone.
Hi and welcome to our panel discussion,
Agentic AI for Higher Education.
And today our goal is to explore the promises
and challenges of agentic AI
and how colleges will be prepared
for this transformative area on AI.
And let me now introduce my panelist.
I'm delighted to introduce President Ajita Talwalker Menon,
she's president and CEO of Calbright College.
And Dr. C, you just saw Dr. C,
she's the head of community learning and growth at Playlab
and Dr. Alison Gurganus,
she is serving as an innovation
and emerging technology faculty specialist
with the San Diego Community College District.
So welcome all,
and if you want to learn more about our panelists,
their work, they're amazing, the stuff that they are doing,
and you can find all the information available
in our website
And thank you all for being here. Welcome.
So I'm gonna like start directly,
don't have much time left.
And let's begin with some clarity.
So how do you define agentic AI
and what distinguishes agentic AI
from the traditional AI tools
that students might already be using?
- I was gonna take that one. I'm also your librarian, but.
(audience cheering)
So we thought we would let you know
for those that haven't quite gotten their hands
around the whole agentic situation.
So we are familiar with large language models,
which is a conversation.
So we speak, we write back and forth.
We have a conversation with our large language model.
And so it's sort of a one way, oh, are we not? Okay.
Is that, there we go. Hi.
So it's a conversation
that we're having with a large language model.
Agentic doesn't just have a conversation with you,
it is a tool that does tasks for you.
So I'll give you an example
that anybody can probably relate to.
Let's say I want go to Oahu
and I don't have time to deal with this.
So what I do is I tell my agent,
"Look, here is my number for American Airlines,
here is the seats I like to sit in.
Here's all the information about my likes
and dislikes about airlines,
and here's all my information about a hotel.
This is the hotel I like to do.
Here's my rewards number for this hotel.
These are the kind of rooms I like to stay in, so go."
And it will make the reservations for me.
Let's say I find out, then I have to go on the fifth
of every month back to Oahu.
Then it will make those reservations
for me and just let me know.
There you go.
Now this is a very simple agent AI system.
They get much more complicated
and they can also talk to one another
as they get more complicated.
So one agent can speak to another agent.
So it's large language models on steroids
and they can do things for us as opposed
to just conversating with us.
- Okay, so, you know, that's impressive
and this distinction between the traditional AI tools
and the agentic AI is kind of transformative.
So I think we'll come to a point
that the agent will do much more stuff for us
and I will hope I'll get into that time soon.
And if we want to move a little bit from the definition
and the technicals, so what human competencies
become more critical in AI augmented workplace,
and should we teach them?
- I'm happy to start.
I think, you know, at Calbright we're indexing very hard
on durable skills.
And these are often skills that we talk about.
We used to talk about them as soft skills
and as we enter this phase where the thing
that we're asking folks to navigate
is not just their educational experience
and their credential,
but increasingly a very uncertain and evolving labor market.
Indexing on those skills becomes very important.
And it's not just the critical thinking
and the collaboration, the communication skills.
It is a hundred percent the skills around resiliency,
emotional quotient,
and our ability to support self-efficacy,
to actually empower our learners to take action
and to vary action as they enter the workforce.
How we teach those skills becomes critically important.
I was having this conversation with Michael Stewart
who is the head of our academic senate,
and also doing some incredible work
as a faculty leader in the system as well around the ability
to contextualize these skills in different discipline
and domain areas so that students actually
have tactical experience interacting with AI tools
and resources as a part
of not just their educational experience,
but as a tool of empowerment, as a tool that allows them
to actually show what they can do in addition to being able
to demonstrate that the learning
that has occurred around those skills.
So I think these are gonna continue to be maybe the sort
of cream that rise to the top in terms
of the skills that are needed
and the more, not just exposure. but coaching interaction
and embedded experiences that students have
in developing those skills
and in being able to showcase those skills,
the more formidable they become as they position for
what will be an ever changing job market.
- And as you mentioned student
and how we should integrate our student
into all this transformative agentic AI world.
What do you think the barriers
that can face us when we want to integrate AI
into the educational system?
Like I will say our community college system,
I want to hear that from like the expert opinion.
So I think knowing those barriers,
maybe will be more prepared to what's coming
and will have better tools
facing all this transformation in the AI world.
- I'm going start the barrier discussion in one thing,
I thought we'd spend a little bit more time
on the opportunity and the power,
but we'll go back to that for sure.
I have to say that one of the things
that feels most important
for every institutional leader in this moment is to move
with intention in this space
and to really look at what is the sort of unsexy work
that has to happen within an institution
and an organization to be AI ready.
And for us,
and I know a number of colleges in this system, I think,
you know, we're working with an incredible organization,
AQL labs, who I think is here somewhere.
So if you encounter them
or seek them out asking about their work along
with MiraCosta College and Long Beach College
and Merced, who are at various stages in examining
as an institution,
what does their technology stack look like?
What does their cloud based infrastructure look like?
How does their data architecture need
to be positioned in order
to support all the exciting opportunities that are out there
to leverage this technology, not just the power that it has,
but the way that it can empower our learners
and empower our institutions to service our students better
and to drive better outcomes for our students.
So that foundational piece is critically important.
We're a bit farther along in that than a lot
of other institutions that I've been talking to.
But if we do that part right, then all the other things
that it unlocks can be extraordinary
and it allows us to retain the agency
as an educational institution that we need to properly
and responsibly oversee the leverage use
of these technologies.
- Yeah, I totally agree.
Having those type of connection, communication
to prepare our student to the agenetic AI
or the future, that brings to my mind
that very important idea
that you are referring to which collaboration.
So everything we can, when we get into a new technology,
a new world, you know, we always, as a higher education
or an educational system, we look always for
how we can collaborate within the industry with institutions
to better prepare our students
or to provide them the school they need to the world
of the agentic AI.
So what do you think, what makes successful partnership
between the higher education
and the industry in the context of AI education?
What shape would look like?
- I'm gonna be biased here if that's okay.
In order to do something,
I'm gonna thread something here,
which is when we think about the skills that are necessary,
I want you to think about what are the purposes
of education?
And we're always pipelining students
in the future workforce,
and that's really important.
That's part of the work of doing, you know,
schooling in a formal manner.
And in the United States context in particular,
so much of our identities are rolled up
in these are my achievements, this is where I work, right?
It's all about our productivity.
And I think what's interesting about what's coming
is that as AI continues to essentially
take away all these things that we identify
as like what makes us like who we are,
we have to really consider the question
of like what does it even mean to be human?
Because agentic AI can do all these things,
it's pretty powerful what it can achieve.
And we have to rethink one, you have to have a mindset shift
around like, okay, not only what does it mean to be human,
but then who am I collaborating with?
And you have to have a relationship almost,
not in this sort of like human way,
but you have to have this,
you have to think about like, okay,
if everything is going to be a machine
and human collaboration,
what role do I play in that
and how do I facilitate these types of relationships?
And as older jobs go away as a result of this kind
of redefining disruptive technology
and even disruptive in the sense of even
what it means to be like human,
what is the future of work even going to be
and what role will I play
and how does that counter with,
I still have bills to pay, right?
And how are we even thinking
about this new economy as a result of that?
So jobs will come, we've seen that, right?
So I always like to quote Kevin Kelly,
he has a book called, The Inevitable:
The 12 Technological Forces that Will Shape Our Future.
He talks about electrification.
So previous to the industrial revolution,
we had farmers at 70%, and then today about 1% is farmers.
And so they would look at our jobs today
and be like, "What the what?" Right?
So we're in that moment,
we're at this inflection point.
And so how do you enable your students, right,
to feel like they can be creators of set futures,
not just receivers of the future,
but if they are change makers,
how do you develop the agency, right, for them to navigate
what is an unknown future, but also to define it.
And so I think that's a critical piece.
And so partnerships, I think, are really important
in terms of there's two orientations, right?
So you have consumer based models
or consumer based companies, which, you know,
in the United States in particular, the goal is AGI, right?
It's a race, it's breaking things no matter
what the consequences we're going forward in this way
and it's not attending necessarily to, well, should we stop,
should we consider, right?
And then you have something like Playlab,
which is very much about
how do we think carefully about this?
And so because we're coming from that point of view,
our partnership focus is really
in leaning into the expertise,
the humans that enable the driving of this change
and the supporting, the empowering
of these change makers to not only take this change
but then move it forward in a particular way
that would be in service to the public good.
And so I think it's critical that if you're gonna partner,
you're really creating spaces for that co-creation
or that co-construction to be able to happen,
and then there's all the sort of operational logistic things
that go with it.
- I actually think the two tie together really nicely.
We've been thinking about that a lot.
There's so many points along the journey
that are gonna be not can we, which used to be the question,
but should we?
And there is, you know, I think we've sort
of just laid out the value on that within our institution
and our organization,
which is like the human is in the loop.
That is a choice because increasingly it may not be required
in a lot of different areas.
So that is a choice to make for a lot
of different organizations and entities,
not just in higher education,
about the future that they're gonna chart.
And I do think it is critically important
to not always accelerate towards the shiniest object
of what could be.
But you know, that when I speak about intentionality
or spoke about intentionality,
it's very much this thing.
How do we empower
and use these tools to supercharge the work
that is largely human driven within our organizations?
Because particularly in the space of education,
there's something important
and sacred about that evolution of the human condition
that is something we're uniquely positioned to do.
And so I love the way that you talked about that,
because I think that's exactly right.
- And to your point, I want you to say something too,
but to your point, like we need to teach our young people
and we need to teach ourselves, AI has its place.
It doesn't empathize, it's not human,
even though it's built to feel that way.
It has its place and you are the boss of it.
And it's really important to understand that,
especially with young people who are having relationships
with it, right?
It's causing real harm.
It's really rethinking what is the role of agentic AI
or AI in particular,
and how do we help people understand it's a tool,
it's a powerful tool,
but understanding the technical like workings of it,
I think help with supporting people
in making those decisions about have it's place,
know how to control it.
If it's your teammate, it's still a machine.
(audience applauding)
- I love that. You know, I love that.
And giving the fact
that our students are relying a lot on AI
and even with the look like, you know,
I will say traditional AI tool, GPTs
and stuff like that,
they were like deeply working with those.
And now we are going into agentic AI like even more.
So what do you think like from your, you know, opinion,
how we can prepare our students
to traditional from using like simple AI
or traditional AI to agentic AI
and the same way we are needed to keep it as ethical,
as responsible as, I will say, humanized as possible?
- Well, you said it, it's AI literacy.
This is AI literacy on another level.
But without that foundation of AI literacy,
you're not gonna get your ethics.
You're not going to get so many things.
You need to understand how to evaluate that output.
You need to understand how to prompt,
you can't have an agent work for you well
unless you know how to tell it what to do.
And that back to the partnerships with industry,
we find that some of the skills that are going
to be needed instead of those baseline skills that may,
those jobs that you first go into,
there will be more managerial jobs that will be talking
to humans and talking to agents,
so you're managing both things.
So when we look at the skills needed by these students,
there's a lot more collaboration needed,
a lot more discussing with one another,
communication skills, project skills.
These become more and more like the durable skills
that you were mentioning, becomes much more important
when we're dealing with these agents,
and it's all based on AI literacy.
And for me, when I go back into barriers,
it's one faculty member at a time
because we need to teach AI literacy to all faculty.
Even if it's no AI in my class, it's okay.
They need to have that conversation though
with why no AI in my class
and you have this class that you can use all the AI
in their class.
What is it about my class that is different?
And they need to be able to discuss these things.
So they have to have a level of AI literacy
that they can have that discussion.
So this is just a baseline that they need to have.
And again, it's one faculty member at a time.
You know, one of the barriers
that I see are faculty members who are just,
it is too much, it's just too much.
And it's affecting their assignments,
it's affecting their assessments.
How can we support them so that they can deal with the fact
that they are not necessarily getting paid
to redo all those assignments and assessments?
So this is how we get to the students is also
through the faculty and we do all the workshops
and we do all of the discussions
and we wanna get them together in disciplined groups
so they can talk amongst themselves.
And we also need them to talk amongst curricular areas
because in the workplace they're dealing
with lots of different areas.
They're not in silos like we are often
in the education system.
So we need to start to level those playing fields
and get people talking amongst one another.
- A hundred percent agree with you.
You know, one code that I use, sorry.
Sorry.
- I love the like taking us from the sort
of learning, knowing.
And I think for our students particularly,
they come to us with a goal in mind, which is a career goal
and so they learn best by the doing.
And one of the other areas when we talk about partnership
that feels really important
is the places which give them opportunities
or the partnerships that give them opportunities
to try these things out.
So we have two partnerships
that I think are particularly exciting for our learners
because they bring them closer to the world
of work in a way that is meaningful
and actually has some transactional value for them.
This incredible partnership with Riipen,
which is a work-based learning platform
and the work with Riipen is particularly instructive
and useful because it gives students an opportunity
to not just play around with tools,
but to actually have that micro internship experience.
To actually have something
that becomes an artifact on their resume
that is not just about the credential,
but is about demonstrating to an employer what they can do
and demonstrating to themselves what they can do
and accomplish.
And similarly, we have a really exciting opportunity
with HubSpot
and the work around HubSpot was really leaning into AI
and technology forward tools in as a CRM platform,
so in the marketing space
and really thinking about, again,
with a micro internship opportunity
or with a work-based learning project,
how can we allow our learners to explore
with partners who will help kind
of facilitate the opportunities that are gonna set them up
for success against their goal,
not our goal as an institution.
So when we talk about collaboration, all the folks
that have to come to the table,
the closer we thread to the folks
that are making those decisions on the demand side,
it becomes very important in terms of the position
and the strength that our learners have
in a very competitive and conflicted job market.
- Can I ask? - Yeah, sure.
- I think that's so cool.
And one more plug for Playlab.
But no, seriously, like so in the summer, for example,
well actually in all my courses,
my students build change maker chatbots.
They identify a problem in community that they care about
and then they build an AI tool that acts as an assistant
to support whatever movement they might be trying to make
or to address specific problems.
And so students create the most meaningful, amazing things.
And then because you can publish that chatbot,
you can share it out,
I've had students put that on their LinkedIn profiles
and have them be able to demonstrate,
I know how to system prompt,
I know how to configure a chatbot.
I know how to,
but you're also embedding the literacy skills within it.
A system prompt is all about understanding the problem,
who your target audience is, leveraging design thinking,
leveraging storytelling,
understanding how to communicate effectively.
How does this chatbot or this AI enable collaboration
or enable you to just extend the impact
of your change making endeavors.
So I love that about literacy.
I think staff is incredibly important.
I don't think we, you know, like it's the whole ecosystem
working together and all of us developing those capacities.
'cause I think the relationship between students
and teachers is also, I think we're in a new world, right,
'cause we're all learning at the same time
as our students are learning these skills.
And so I just wanted to highlight that,
that it's the opportunity for people to be able to build
is such an incredible skill
that will serve them well going forward,
especially when the workplace will demand you to be able
to know how to effectively work with AI and agents.
- I love what you also said about the connection
between the learner and the educator that's shifting.
This idea of a conversation between them.
And I'm flashing back to my child just discovered ChatGPT
and the first thing she did
was design an American girl doll in her likeness.
And then she, it is a hilarious feed.
I will happily share out.
But you know, the next jump she made was she was asked
to do some homework around the states.
And so she said, "I'm gonna ask ChatGPT for my states.
And I said, "Wait a second,
talk to me a little bit about how you're using it."
And the conversation she had was,
"Well, I know I meant sources.
So I was taught to research and to get sources
and beyond Google, I'm gonna use this."
And I was like, "Okay."
So she went through this thing,
it seemed credible from my perspective,
but I'm not her teacher.
And so I said, "Listen, I think it's really important
that you talk to your teacher about how you're using this,
understand her expectations about it,
clarify her expectations about it.
Show her what you're doing, show show her your work."
And it was just a moment when I was reflecting on it
when you said that,
where I thought, yeah,
that is actually such an important part of the teaching
and learning process now.
And it's not just because people, you know,
it's not a cheating conversation.
It's actually, I'm not sure where the lines are.
How do we actually bring out, draw out
and assess where those can be?
And if that varies by the person who is at the front
of the classroom, you know, how do we give, you know,
our learners the sort of skills to kind
of have those kinds of conversations?
Very different.
- Yeah, mentioning your director,
I have a faculty that's teaching AI,
she developed a chatbot for her families
that has all the schedule, the kids schedule this morning.
And yeah, every family was sharing that
and it was fantastic.
She was on Daylight, Nectar all those
and she got it from that.
I think extending this outside school, outside,
it's also literacy, it's also AI literacy.
Like we are people, you know,
outside the education environment are learning
about AI are developing, are using AI.
And that will be even preparing them better
for the new AI era.
And one code that I use it for all my,
because I'm one of the AI nerds in my school
and some people like will say, "We are anti AI,
we will not accept AI."
So one code that I keep using it in all my presentation
is for Roseville.
Like when change come, the best thing
to do one is the, I will say,
the one thing to do is the best thing
and the worst thing to do is to do nothing.
So the worst thing is to do nothing.
So we don't want just to, you know, do nothing about AI.
We all need to be, you know,
changing all the way that we are learning, using,
working to be prepared for the AI.
And we talked about industry, we talk about student slide,
now because this is this full community call.
So as a community call system,
what do you think like one concrete thing,
one main action that can community college
do immediately to be better prepare students
for the agentic AI?
- I'm trying to think of something
that I did not say a minute ago.
Yeah, it's the AI literacy.
I keep going back, and the ethics,
understanding how to communicate
with each other and with the tools.
Somehow finding ways to get that to everyone,
classified professionals, administrators, students, faculty,
because it's foundational
and we can't get to the next level
until we have that foundation.
And people learn differently.
So maybe for some it means playing with the tool first
and then realizing I can't get where I wanna go,
what do I need to do?
And helping them at that level.
Sometimes it's getting them into a session,
explaining how things work
to give them the permission to put their toe in the water
or the permission to start using chatbots
or the permission to ask about agents
and see what's going on.
Also, people get overwhelmed
and I try and let them know
that perhaps it's best to stay in their lane.
The landscape can get dystopian and it can get scary,
but if we focus on what is affecting us
and what we need to do to respond, that is helpful.
You see something in the chronicles of higher ed
that talks about gen AI and education.
I'm in education, gen AI is affecting me, let me read that.
You hear something on national public radio,
you hear something wherever, this is very helpful.
And to get people to understand that constant learning,
that constant keeping up in your lane is very,
very helpful.
It's the librarian in me, right?
Research and information is my jam, you know?
But if I was AI literate in 2023
and I did nothing between 2023 and now,
I'm no longer AI literate.
So keeping up with that
and keeping that around is of the utmost importance
and those are actions that can be done now.
We can continue,
once you've done a series of workshops,
there's a series of people that did not get those workshops,
so they need to be continued, and at levels.
We have to support these sessions
and really get this professional development to all levels
as much as we possibly can.
(audience applauding)
- I agree with what you said.
I think yes and you know, leaning into the community part
of community college feels critically important
in this moment.
And sometimes we think our community is the four corners
of our institution,
and this is an important opportunity
that if it is not our institutions
that are getting out there
and supporting the overall AI literacy capabilities
of the communities we operate in,
that is an extraordinary disservice.
I think we have a unique responsibility
and also a unique vantage point in which to do that.
We are leaning very heavily into that space to be able
to find more instances where we can provide,
you know, content or learning support
that can be self navigated,
that can be a tool and a resource.
I know this is a big priority
for the chancellor under her vision
and it's something we're excited to contribute to,
but I think it really does take everyone in the room
in the privileged position that we sit in to do that,
because what is happening out there
if left to its own devices
and what is being imposed upon our community members
is frightening and you know, careens us towards
that dystopian state.
And whether it's within K-12 public education
or community college public education,
we have an extraordinary opportunity
to do something differently
and to chart a course that's different
for our communities to thrive
given a lot of this is happening
in such a wildly deregulated environment
and in a way where there is not clarity
or transparency around how these technologies come into play
and how they interact and are used in our everyday lives.
And so I just wanna emphasize,
I don't wanna leave this conversation without taking
that charge on, you know, as an entire system.
(audience applauding)
- I'll just add that I think a key skill that we need
to make sure everyone develops is the ability
to learn how to learn.
So question for the audience:
How do you think I've developed my expertise?
And expertise, I hold loosely, agentic AI.
What do you think?
How have I learned that?
(audience chatting)
AI taught me.
(audience laughing)
I talked to AI, I spent a lot of days with Claude,
my friend there, and just asking it questions
like what is agentic AI?
How does that even work?
What do you mean it can call tools?
What is a vector?
What, a token?
I have no idea what you're talking about.
Break it down for me like I'm five.
And I think that's what's powerful about AI is
that it enables all of us to be able
to meet ourselves where we're at.
And then the key components are really critically thinking
about the outputs, understanding how AI works
as a probability machine.
It's non-deterministic.
How many times have you written an email
or a draft of something you are like, "Hey ChatGPT,
I really like this section,
but the rest of this like just focus
on revising that section
and then just keep everything else the same."
And then what happens?
It rewrites whole damn thing.
And that's because it's non-deterministic.
It's using probabilities around what the next word should be
and it's math, right?
And so I think understanding that
and then understanding that agentic AI is
about pairing these large language models
and the power that it has to be able
to sort of like make these predictions about
what likely goes together
with tools that make it deterministic.
So okay, you have student data,
so I'm making maybe an assignment in my class.
I'm really trying to evaluate.
Maybe I create an assessment
that is enabling itself to meet a student.
Like maybe you need it to be done in Spanish.
Maybe this needs to come down another level,
or it needs to be giving you different kinds of examples.
So the large language model enables that interaction
with that student.
The agentic part is maybe it is embedding certain tools
that keep it consistent
where it's like, oh, okay, it's working with a rubric.
It's able to grade through a rubric
because it's a calling, a tool, what's attached to your LMS.
And so that's the power of that.
And I think as you move forward, it's much more about
how do you create conditions that enable people
to develop the muscle around,
I'm a lifelong learner. I will always need to learn.
My favorite author, as I was just saying,
has this concept of becoming.
The tools themselves are always becoming.
You were just saying, like if you stop, it was just a week.
In the week, I feel like oh my god, I'm so behind, right?
And so if you stop, you know, you lose., right?
And so how do we enable ourselves to love learning,
be curious, to be playful with it
and to enable ourselves to use this tool.
How do you encourage students or young people
or people in general to develop that muscle?
You've gotta be a lifelong learner
and that will keep you afloat in
what is a very precarious kind of world we're navigating.
It will enable you to have a voice, enable you to say
what you think this should be,
to be at tables that you would otherwise not avail yourself
or be present at if you don't take the time
to be a self learner.
And so I think even orienting our systems around that.
Like how do you construct learning experiences,
classroom experiences where we have to learn
how to learn is essentially what it comes down to.
It's a skill, it's a necessary one to, I think,
survive in this future.
(audience applauding)
- So I'm a faculty
and maybe I forget at the beginning,
I'm the Folsom Lake College AI department chair.
I always go to my dean with like maybe, you know, 20 plans
for the three more semester.
You know, when such faculty come to be,
"Oh my god, she's here again."
So I'm that person with a lot of class.
So always I like to have that future look
what will happen next, how we can prepare.
So from your opinion,
where we will see agentic AI in five years?
- My hope is we'll see it,
and there are ethical issues to this that we do need privacy
and security issues that we need to be very concerned about.
I see a system
that can go into your student services records,
see that a student has been availing themself
of certain services.
It can go into Canvas and show the last five essays
and the fact that they've been doing less
and less in each essay
and can go into various aspects where you get the idea
and can then tell the instructor, "Hey, you know,
you're losing this student.
This student might be dropping out
and they're not getting this content area,
so maybe you should go to this student
and give them this kind of feedback about, you know,
get them excited about that content
and get them more excited about the class."
They could also, for example,
an instructor could see all of their students information
and be able to tell that everybody's getting all the content
except for this.
Why? I'm suddenly able to see that.
And then the agentic AI can help them
create the lesson plans
that can get them back on track with that
and differentiate that instruction.
So my athletes are not doing as well
as the others also in that area,
so how can I differentiate the instruction
for those students?
And it can help them create those lessons.
So the things coming together to help us do the work
that we want to do in a more productive manner.
Get to the reason we we got to education in the first place.
We can get back to that without having to go
through every single solitary essay.
No, no. How is it about that?
You know, and this is of course only
from the faculty perspective,
but this is something that I would hope to see
within to five years.
And having this be normal,
not something special, having this kind of thing
be something that just helps us get better at what we do.
- So I'll say like we're kind of there right now
at the foundational stages of putting that into place.
And I'll say two things about it.
One is, you know, conceptually calling this
like a Calbright, like a student learning engine.
And the idea is how do you from an end-to-end experience
connect all the dots of available understanding
to get that 360 view of a learner.
So it is important for our faculty to have access
and understanding of what's happening in a student's life,
just as it is important for our counseling staff
and student support specialists to have that.
And largely the lead from that
comes from the learners themselves.
So the reason that college was possible for them
and the reason they chose to do it
with us at Calbright
and the responsibility that we have to that
has to do with the fact that it was flexibly paced
but it was fully supported.
And so everything that we do in terms
of empowering our faculty, our staff,
whether it's counseling or student support specialists
or IT support who are student facing,
is about giving the proper amount of visibility
to the things that will allow us to get ahead of proactively
what our learners need.
And so when I talk about the data architecture
and infrastructure that's necessary
to really leverage these tools in service
of student success, right?
In service of students' own goals, their own progression
and stronger outcomes for them,
those are the pieces that have to come together
and we're kind of laying the foundation
for those pieces right now within the technology side.
It's a little bit different for us,
largely because, you know,
we've been built from the ground up to be digitally enabled.
But I do think, you know, the more
that institutions progress at unifying data
across the institution, the faster we will get
to the vision you're describing.
It can be really powerful if we do it
and move in ways that are intentional.
- I was just gonna say that data is really power.
Like the California Community College systems
reflect like data and you kind of have to pick sides.
I'm gonna end with that.
Meaning, think about when you're using a tool
when it comes to AI, whose interests are at play?
I heard recently for example, like when you get something
for free it's 'cause you're the product.
That data is what enables these large language models to do
what they do and that they are data hungry
and they continue to consume.
So there's power in being able to say,
we're gonna hold our data in a protected way
so that it's in service to our students
and to these educational objectives
versus other reasons why.
Partnerships may be about,
we really want to work with you in the K-12.
So like Google, right?
Google is in the K-12 system.
Those are early brand users, right?
We need to think critically about are there alignments
in the kinds of partnerships
or the tools we're using? - A hundred percent.
- Because power is coming from that data.
So that'll be my closing statement.
Pick five.
(audience applauding)
- Thank you. I know which side I'm gonna take.
I know, we're all the same side.
(laughing) - Yes, I think so.
So I think today we see our agentic AI is more
than technical rule, it is a shifting paradigm,
taking us from all the,
I would say, usual simple AI tool that used to
and provide more opportunities, more innovation,
but also it'll bring some barriers,
it'll bring some challenges.
But I think we are ready to face all that
and I think we are on time.
And let me, on behalf of the Future Summit 2025,
thank you to our panelists.
(audience applauding)
So I wanna stop here
and as we are shaping our future,
we will continue discussing, innovating,
and meeting and working together.
Thank you all.
(audience applauding)